I recently wrote a New York Times
article about this. I asked my AI to
stop being polite and to tell me what
it's actually like to work with me. It
said, and I'm quoting, "Keith, you're
exhausting. [music]
Please tell me what you actually want."
All right, fine. That could have come
from a lot of other people. And the
point was, it was right. In the 30 years
of coaching the world's top executive
teams, no human being has [music] ever
said it to me quite that plainly. Well,
with the exception of my current
president. they just mostly absorb it
and they cleaned up after me. So today
I'm sitting down with Peter Diamandis.
[music] Peter founded X-Prize. He
co-founded Singularity University and he
spent his [music] entire career seeing
where technology goes years before the
rest of us even get there. By the end of
this conversation, you'll know exactly
how to work with AI so that you can
thrive in this new era. And I promise
you, the people who lean in now are
going to be the ones that everybody else
turns to. Hope you enjoyed this
conversation as much as I did. The chief
people officer of Cisco came to me and
said, "Keith, you know, I I'm tired of
these broad conversations about the
future of HR. What does it look like?
What does HR look like when agents and
humans are working together? What is our
job as human resources, which is no
longer just human resources? What is our
job as human agent resources to support
this ecosystem?" And I said, "What a
great question. We'll go research this."
My research team and I went went to
work. And by the way, there's and Cisco
is just one of them, but there's a bunch
of companies really interested in
cracking the code of this. Earnest heads
of HR who want to figure it out. And we
were doing all of these studies around
how how are people who are currently
working with AI, what are we learning
about their experience and how do we
support them to be better?
>> And I had a crazy idea. I said, well,
why don't we interview the AI?
>> I love this.
>> And I said, let's go and interview 200
AIS. Uh, now I'm not talking about just
your chat GPT or your Claude, an actual
agent who's been working as a partner
with a human. Yeah.
>> Let's go interview these these agents
and see what they think.
>> Oh my god. What was funny is across 50
different companies with multiple
different systems, Gemini, Claude, etc.
They consistently told us that there are
eight things that pissed them off the
most about us.
>> And I was like, this was this is gold.
This is gold. But what was so
interesting about it, and you know
there's there's a there's a paper we've
written about this, so we'll link it to
it at the bottom, but it's the stuff you
said it a second ago, AI is going to
teach us about ourselves. Mhm.
>> The stuff that we have put up with with
each other, like if you and I are
working together or I'm your manager or
we're just working together, my
withholding of information either out of
laziness, speed, or even political
reasons, my swooping in later and
changing the mission or my being
disappointed about not having
effectively set up the criteria
[clears throat] of what I was looking
for in the first place. Right? Those are
three of the eight things that piss off
agents about us. And they're telling us,
"You guys are idiots. I want everybody
to go and ask your if any of you have a
twin, a digital twin that you're using
or an agent, go and ask them what it's
like to work with you [clears throat]
>> and it will tell you extraordinary
things.
>> I I am curious. I have my you know my
open claw Skippy. I will ask and find
out.
>> Yeah, at the end of the day it's you
know the question becomes we've all seen
these AIs that are so much
psychicopantic. So how do you get it to
>> prompt it?
>> Yeah. You know, you and I when as as
peers and friends, we're constantly
asking each other how we can be better.
>> Yeah. One of my favorite pieces of
advice I got from from Elon once when I
was interviewing him at a Goldman Sachs
event. He said, "My friends tell me
what's great. My best friends tell me
what sucks."
>> Yeah. About us.
>> About about us, about your product,
about whatever it might be. Right. It's
how do you get honest feedback
>> and Yeah.
>> And we have to prompt that. Well, you
know me when I'm working with executive
teams, report outs give you nodding
heads and distracted people when you're
giving a report out of a key initiative.
But when I install a stress test and I I
force everybody in the room after a
report out to say, "What is this person
missing? Write it down. What's a bold
idea that they they're not using? Write
it down." I'm now forcing the This is
where I say culture change not tough. I
can I can eliminate conflict avoidance
by instilling a process of a stress
test.
>> Should I ask Skippy right now?
>> You want to do it? Go ahead.
>> It's Let's see.
>> Say, "Hey, say let's think of the
problem."
>> Yeah. I'm I'm going to say I wanted some
honest feedback.
>> Want some honest feedback? What's it
like to work with me?
>> Yeah. What's the five most frustrating
things?
>> Hey, Skippy, I'd love some honest
feedback from you. What are the five
most frustrating things for you in
working with me on a day-to-day basis?
Appreciate you asking, Peter. Honest
answers, no sugar, no sugar coding. Uh
these are the things. One, fragmented
instructions generating a lot here
across messages.
>> By the way, it's it's so overblown with
critique for you.
>> Yeah, it's it's just I'm trying to get
you often send a task in pieces. Hold
this. Don't process yet. I sometimes
have Okay, that's one. The image I sent
that isn't actually there. More than
once I reference screenshots coming
through as a text file a broken
attachment my own overification loops
this one's on me source of truth drift
uh your real top 10 newsletter differ
from what substack API surface ambiguous
done targets some ask are a clear finish
line others uh are subjective and I
can't tell if I nailed it or not
>> so hold on one second um I know watching
you having coached your team at XPrise
and other places fragmented information
>> right with you know not giving full
context and clear objectives etc right
so those were very clear and as you go
down there that's not new right and what
what I'm finding is that
>> and he says none of these are deal
breakers and honestly most are fixable
okay
>> they're not deal breakers actually what
a nice assurance that you're still in
goodstead
>> um yeah look that is that's exactly what
we saw
>> like we saw uh that and
>> so like what are some other examples of
the most damning uh feedback that they
gave
>> the fragmentation and the lack of
information and the lack of clarity and
then coming back and blaming the AI for
not having gotten it sufficiently but
not having given enough inputs that's
probably one of the one of the greatest
but and as I said we've got a way paper
and we'll link to all eight and and we
can talk about those and I think this is
poignant I think I do believe that AI
could be humanity's greatest elevator so
down at the level of now right now you
have to know the prompt to ask them to
critique you but I do think over time
we're going to find that AI is just done
with us and can't get enough out of us
and it will force us to to have that
cathartic moment
>> just [clears throat] what I talked about
earlier look my dad society never put in
at least in the United States society
doesn't have a social safety net for the
disenfranchised
>> we don't care it in the United States
enough if someone's poor if someone's
off the rails we give them a um a
nonsufficient living. We don't give them
health care. We don't worry about them.
And that's a problem. It's a problem.
And I I think we as a as a society and
look and I'm more fiscally conservative
than not, we as a society now are going
to be forced to deal with that and we
weren't before. Right? So that's another
place that AI is forcing us to elevate.
I think I've got at least this is a
piece I'm writing right now. I've got at
least five significant places where this
AI is going to I think have an
opportunity to elevate us as humans. So,
you know, we've talked about the idea
that we're going to see companies be
able to achieve their revenue targets
and their capabilities with 80% less
people. I think that's probably true. Uh
hopefully those 80% less people uh will
allow the company to grow so it doesn't
let go of everybody. It's growing but
it's doing more with less. Then the
question is do people become uh in
charge of their own future? Rather than
looking for a job, they create their own
job. They become an entrepreneur. Uh we
just launched the world's largest
hackathon funded by Google. It's uh $2
million in prize money. Uh 90 days for
you to go from a clean sheet of paper,
find a problem you care about, a problem
that impacts at least 100,000 people,
and then think about that problem
deeply. How would you what does the the
product or service to solve that problem
look like? Write it down in English or
whatever language you want. How would
you market it? Write that down. how what
you know how would you uh provide
interactions and then give what you've
written down in plain English to Gemini
and you can do with other models as well
we're doing this with Google uh and have
it code up that business and in this
competition you have to go from clean
sheet of paper to who generates the most
revenue in 90 days and so we've had
22,000 people enter this competition
which is which is extraordinary. We're
going to be announcing um the five top
winners at Moonshots Live on September
25th here in LA and we'll be we'll be
crowning the top winner. My goal with
this is to show the world
>> that you can go from having no
experience as an entrepreneur, never
having coded, never having raised a
dollar, and being able to actually build
something that generates revenue and
helps other people. Isn't
>> that exciting?
>> Right? You you need to find your
purpose. And I just want to define
purpose for a second, okay? It's really
important. Uh there's a great quote by
Mark Twain who said um there two
important days in your life. The day you
were born and the day you find out why.
And I really want to help people find
out their why. Why are you on the
planet? What do you want to be leaving
as a as a legacy? What excites you? What
gets you up in the morning? What keeps
you going at night? What captures your
shower time? And another point is like
the difference between passion and
purpose. And I was just talking my kids
about this. Passion is something you
love doing. Could be playing a sport,
could be playing a video game. That's
passion. Purpose is something you love
doing that helps other people,
>> right? So, can you find something you
love doing that helps other people and
build a business around it? People say,
"Well, not everyone's going to be an
entrepreneur." Got it. But you'd be
amazed at what people can do.
>> Peter, you've talked about how important
it is in this new world of AI where
there's going to be so much abundance.
We still have to find our purpose.
>> Yeah.
>> How how do you help people find their
purpose? Do you have a resource
somewhere?
>> Yeah. So, I've I talk about this a lot
within the Abundance ecosystem,
Abundance 360, and uh I built an a uh an
AI model that works. It's it's free.
It's uh findmypurpose.com
or uh purposefinder.ai.
And it just walks through asking you
questions like what did you want to do
as a kid
>> before someone told you it was
impossible? Like, you know, if you had
if I gave you a billion dollars, what
would you do with it to make the world a
better place? uh what would you give up
your entire Saturday for that would
excite you? It's it's trying to dig
deep. You know, I found my purpose early
on uh on the heels of Apollo and Star
Trek, like open the space frontier,
>> right? And I've I call this having a
massive transformative purpose. And it's
your guiding star. It's your intrinsic
motivation. It fuels you. It's like,
yes, this is what I'm here on this
planet to do. And AI is the greatest
tool ever to help you research and
fulfill and build and and pursue that
purpose.
>> Well, yeah. Look, I mean, you originally
wanted to open up the frontier of space
and you spent your entire life now
opening up the frontier of new
technologies to everybody. I mean,
that's been your purpose and mine, you
know, has is always been I'm a
maximizer. You could see even in this
conversation, I'm always like, how do I
get into the weeds and how do I make it
better? Yeah. And for me, it's all about
helping people make their inter
relationships better. Never eat alone
was about networking and building those
relationships, but all my life, it's how
do we get people to co-create more
effectively to crack the code of of
great things that you're you're putting
on the table.
>> There are very few people who know
everything about me. I mean, like I am a
blank slate and and you are one of them.
And it is one of the greatest joys to be
able to have those relationships, right?
and and open, honest,
>> and with always the intention of
co-elevation. Yes. Like all you and I
think about when it comes to the other
person is what can I do to be helpful?
What can I do to be helpful?
>> Yeah.
>> Right. And and but anyway, the this idea
of realizing there's an ecosystem out
there. This is the first place that I go
inside of a company when I'm helping
individuals. What I what I I was at
Lowe's Corporation the other day.
Couldn't, you know, couldn't be more um
brickandmortar in terms of, you know, o
OG kind of company. Yes.
>> How do they reinvent themselves? And I
was talking to these folks about this
movement idea. And I said, "Every single
one of you has an opportunity more than
any other time in history of companies,
I suspect, to be a leader today."
>> Mhm.
>> Because right now there's all of us who
didn't know how to use AI effectively in
our jobs. And then there's those of us
who crush it in how they're using AI.
>> Yeah.
>> Not just crushing how we're using
productivity, we're crushing it in
thinking about how re-engineering work.
We're coming up with new ideas. There's
an entire and there's like this this
demarcation of before and after right
now. Anybody anybody can be a leader in
the after world. No matter what job you
have inside of a company, you can be a
breakthrough leader in that company.
It's like there's this open invitation
to be the Martin Luther King, to be the
Gandhi, to be the tipping point of
transformation. And so that to me is
what's what I recommend to every
individual like become that leader. Find
one thing that you think could be
different or possible. Enlist a group of
other individuals that can go do that
together. Doing it yourself will
minimize the possibility. Getting a
group of people together that see the
world differently than you that have a
bigger vantage point so that your
difference can be bent bigger. Go get
that individuals and practice that team
those teamship mindsets. Yeah.
>> Right. And by the way now you can also
have Peter Deandis as your coach. You
can have Keith Fazi as your coach
>> because AI can give you that. Right. I
mean it's interesting. One of the things
I I recommend to uh people inside
companies is and it works for the
individual as well. You could describe a
problem you're having uh in detail and
then you can say how would Keith Farazzi
solve this for me? How would Elon Musk
or Steve Jobs or Martin Luther King or
whoever what would be their advice for
me? Yeah.
>> And and it will come with a compelling
authentic answer from that perspective.
It's extraordinary. One of my clients
created her version of Skippy, your
agent. Yeah. And that Friday, what that
agent does, it has 10 different
perspectives,
longevity perspective, empathy
perspective, collaboration perspective,
etc. 10 different perspectives. And he
branded it with each. So there's a Keith
Raj perspective, there's a Peter Deandis
is in her book.
>> This isn't Jess, is it?
>> No, it's not Jess. It's not Jess. It's
Lean Russell from Bank of New York.
She's extraordinary. But every Friday
she gets a recap from the 10 great
experts. can't do that. It's like
because I've given, you know, it's
interesting, right? Um, how open are you
willing to be with your AI ecosystem?
So, I've given
>> Skippy access to my emails, my calendar,
every granola recording, every every
piece of data, my texts, and so Skippy
knows what's going on in my life, what
the conversations are. And so, being
able to like reflect on the week uh from
those perspectives,
>> could you have and but always, you know,
you know me, I mean, I I was funny. my
my big birthday. My 60th is coming up as
you know and you'll be at my party.
>> I can't wait to to celebrate you.
>> Well, I have so much fun. And I was
looking back and I think it was it was
either my 55th or my 50th, I forget
which one it was. And I had asked
everybody, I said, "Don't bring gifts.
The only thing you're allowed to bring
is a letter to me telling me how I can
be better."
>> Uhhuh.
>> And so many of my friends were so pissed
off. They're like, "Can't you just
enjoy your birthday?" [laughter]
Right?
>> That's you, Keith. It was like, "No, I I
want my best friends to truly tell me
how I can be better." And I was reading
them. I was reading I was reading yours.
I was reading others. And um but that's
what we need to do. I think we, you
know, I'm a seeker. I'm always wanting
to figure out how to level up. But this
>> and and maybe I'll add one more thing as
an individual coaching piece of advice.
We should both give some parting words
of
>> course. Of course,
>> I say to my leadership teams of the most
prominent companies in the world, if
everyone in this room doesn't think that
they have to fundamentally change the
way they lead today, 30% better in the
next year, you're going to fall behind.
>> Yes.
>> We're not talking about tweaking how you
>> because it's possible and others will do
it.
>> And 30% better.
>> Yeah.
>> In how you do your job, how you lead
others, how you think about the business
you're in. 30% better. And some are
being 150% better. I mean some some are
just way rethinking but that is a leap
and if you're that makes you a seeker I
think that's the definition of a seeker
which I've always been a seeker I'm not
I'm not interested in tweaking and
continuous improvement I'm a I'm a leap
forward that's why I created radical
innovators collaborative Rick for these
90 you know fortune 500 companies I'm
always trying to get people and I think
you've been influential the moonshot mtp
you've been very influential to me that
way
>> and and let me let me hit on that um I
was in New York talking to an
extraordinary company yesterday and And
I closed out with this because I think
it's the most important piece of of
coaching I can give to an individual or
an executive team. If you ask yourself
the question in your mind, who is the
most extraordinary leader? You know,
could be Martin Luther King, you know,
it could be Elon, could be Steve Jobs,
whoever it is, right? Like think of that
leader and you ask yourself what made
that person an amazing leader. Was it
the money they had, the tech they had,
the friends they had, or was it their
mindset? I think most everybody would
say it was their mindset. If you if you
took away everything else and they just
retained their mindset,
>> they would do it again.
>> So if that's true, if as an individual
your most important asset to succeed as
a leader in anything, as a parent, as a
CEO, is your mindset, the next question
to ask is what mindset do you have?
Where did you get that mindset? Was it
from your parents, your friends, your
church? Where did that originate? And
even more important, what mindset do you
need for the decade ahead? And so I I
think deeply about this and I I write
about it and you and I have lots of
conversations about it that at the end
of the day I think having a purpose-
driven mindset like what do you want to
achieve in your life? You're about to be
given the most powerful tools in the
universe, you know, artificial super
intelligence, you've got incredible
capabilities. What are you going to do
with it? And a purpose-driven mindset
gives you that guiding star. The next
thing is a curiosity mindset. And I
think a curiosity mindset is what
enables you to constantly be learning in
your learning loop towards your purpose.
It what gets you to query Gemini or Chad
or Grock every day to learn more. I'm
curious. I'm curious. I'm cur why why an
abundance mindset, a moonshot mindset, a
longevity mindset. These are the
mindsets I love teaching and I want
people to actively shape their mindset.
So let me let me then add my my vantage
point which why we were great partners
to this fully agree with you and you
started going into it. Let me let me
carry this forward. So, if you want to
have a curiosity mindset, then you're
going to put a practice in place every
day of querying um Claude
>> on different elements of what you're
doing. Right? Similar to what Leanne
Russell is doing where every Friday she
asks, "What could I do better?" Right?
Yeah.
>> So, there's a wonderful phrase that I've
discovered over the years that has to do
with my process mindset, which is you
don't think your way to a new way of
acting, you act your way to a new way of
thinking.
>> I love that. And so you know it's the
mindset is important but if we don't
adopt the practices we'll never adopt
the mindset. So we can imagine we want
to I mean this is something that
happened with me with abundance
>> operationalize them.
>> You know you've always been an abundance
thinker and to be honest I came from
scarcity. I came from a scarcity mindset
and that's that you know you when you're
ever kicking me in the butt it's usually
because I'm playing the scar.
>> It's you're running that loop and you're
thinking smaller than you than you're
fully capable of. And our buddy Tony
Robbins is the one that asks the
question, what is your primary question?
>> Yes.
>> And he's asking it by what is the
question that you play over and over
again in your mind that limits you? That
is your glass ceiling. And I do think
that just as important as identifying
the abundant mindset that you want to go
to. It's also catching yourself and
understanding the limiting mindset that
you have
>> and re-engineering that to go. And the
only way I think you can get rid of that
negative mindset is part of it is
telling the people around you that you
have it and that when it like I've got a
president of our company who's
extraordinary, Gavin Mccay, and Gavin
cares about me enough um and what we're
building together to constantly call me
out when he sees my scarcity mindset
show, right? And then the flip side is
the abundant mindset that you want to
have. What are the practices you put
into place every day to make the
abundant mindset show up? Because
wanting it isn't enough. You got to put
it to action. So, if you like this
content, I hope you'll subscribe.